Guide to the Beth El Synagogue Records, 1881-2012 and undated RL.11336
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Beth El Synagogue records
1881-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Beth-El Synagogue (Durham, N.C.)
RL.11336
15 Linear Feet
4.68 Gigabytes
Beth El Synagogue is a Jewish congregation in Durham, N.C. The collection consists of organizational records for Beth El Synagogue including records related to the synagogue's governance, general membership, the Beth El Sisterhood, the Beth El Preschool, synagogue buildings, and other topics. Materials include committee reports; financial reports; correspondence; printed material, including Books of Life, programs from services, newsletters, and other publications about Jewish history; documentation about the operations of Beth-El Preschool; legal papers; financial papers; photographs of the synagogue, congregation, and programs; and subject files documenting changes in the synagogue's constitutions, construction of new synagogue buildings in 1921 and 1957, dedication services, and the careers of rabbis.
Biographical / Historical
Mainly comprised of German and Eastern European immigrants as well as Russian-Jewish cigarette rollers, the Durham Hebrew Congregation organized in 1887 and rented a hall on Main Street. James B. Duke had formed a contract with Ukrainian immigrant Moses Gladstein to bring over a hundred workers from New York to roll cigarettes in Duke's tobacco factories. Duke automated the factory in 1884 and dismissed the Jewish workers. Most returned north, but several, including Gladstein, chose to remain and opened stores in Durham. As the population continued to slowly grow, the congregation formally chartered in 1892 and hired a rabbi. In 1905 they purchased a small, wood-framed church on Liberty Street, which became Durham's first synagogue. By 1910 the Jewish population in the area had reached approximately 305.
After the First World War, the congregation built a large, cathedral-style synagogue downtown at the intersection of Holloway and Queen Streets. Upon its dedication in 1921, they took the name Beth El Congregation. The congregation remained Orthodox throughout the 1930s and 1940s, but in 1948 hired a rabbi who was a member of the conservative movement. Despite significant internal tensions, the congregation shed its dominant orthodoxy by the mid 1950s. The congregation broke ground on a new, contemporary "American" synagogue on Watts and Markham Streets in 1957; the old structure became the Bethel Baptist Church with a primarily African American congregation. Durham took over and demolished the building in the late 1960s for urban renewal. The location is now the northwest corner of WTVD, the local ABC news affiliate for Durham.
By its centennial year, 1987, the congregation was known as Beth El Synagogue, and had not only successfully created a strategy to accommodate both its modern leanings and orthodox heritage but also helped create other Jewish congregations such as Judea Reform. Beth El had also embraced women as ritual and lay leaders in the 1970s, and the creation of the adjacent Freedman Center in 1987 allowed the congregation to further expand its community service and social action programs. Today, as part of a Jewish population of approximately 8,000 in the Durham-Chapel Hill community, Beth El defines itself as "a vibrant, dynamic community led by a volunteer board, enriched with the teachings of many dedicated community members."
Provenance
The Beth El Synagogue Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1998, 2014, and 2021.
Collection Overview
The Beth El Synagogue Records are divided into five series: Administration, Jewish History, Photographs, Printed Materials, and Programming. The Administration series contains documents relevant to the congregation's organizational records, and is divided into four subseries: Beth El Preschool, Board and Governance, Correspondence, and Subject Files. Jewish History primarily consists of historical accounts of Jewish life in Durham and Chapel Hill, and includes personal biographies of several congregant members. Photographs document congregant members and synagogue events. The series also includes formal portraits of congregant presidents and rabbis. Printed Materials includes newspaper clippings from throughout the twentieth century, primarily from the Durham Morning Herald. Also includes a variety of professional publications related to Jewish life. Programming includes copies of the synagogue's newsletter, the Beth El Bulletin, assorted service bulletins, and a dedication book to commemorate the construction of the new synagogue on Markham and Watts Streets in Durham. The collection also includes materials related to the Women's League for Conservative Judaism, and the organization of events to celebrate Jewish traditions.
Related Materials
Related collections also held in the Rubenstein Library include: Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection of Jewish Historical Materials, 1888-2014; Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Records, 1750-2014 and undated; Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Oral History Collection, 1981-2014; North Carolina Temple and Synagogue Historical Collection, 1926-2010 and undated; Evans Family Papers, 1920s-1990s.
Arrangement
The collection arrived partially sorted and has been divided into five series: Administration, Jewish History, Photographs, Printed Materials, and Programming.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Jewish families -- North Carolina; Jewish religious education of children -- North Carolina; Synagogues -- North Carolina; Rabbis -- North Carolina; Jewish women -- United States.; Nursery schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Photographs -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham County (N.C.); Jews -- North Carolina -- History; Machine-readable artifacts; Beth-El Synagogue (Durham, N.C.)
- Administration, 1881-2009; undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Administration series contains documents relevant to the congregation's organizational records, and is divided into four subseries: Beth El Preschool, Board and Governance, Correspondence, and Subject Files. Beth El Preschool contains documents from the Carnival of the Arts, including publicity materials and financial summaries. The subseries includes extensive financial records of the preschool, including tax reports, payment records, and supplies expenditures. Also includes teacher applications, letters to parents, and information of the preschool's founding. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  The Board and Governance subseries contains meeting minutes of the congregation's leadership, including the board of directors and board of trustees, from 1939-2008. Includes several bound volumes of handwritten meeting notes with various handouts taped in, including: form letters, financial reports, budgets, requests, and typed notes. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Correspondence mostly consists of official correspondence between the Synagogue leadership with various individuals and official organizations, including the American Association for Jewish Education, American Zionist Youth Commission, Hebrew Theological College, United Synagogue of America, and Yeshiva University. Also includes official correspondence with Rabbi Steven Sagar from the 1980s while he served the congregation. Arranged chronologically by year.
  Subject Files contain a variety of organizational records from the synagogue, including financial records, legal papers such as deeds and congregant constitutions, membership lists, staff meeting minutes, Ladies' Aid Society meetings, Beth El Sisterhood meetings, and historical accounts of the synagogue. Also includes two Books of Life, extensive information on funeral rituals and preparation, Chevra Kadisha, and documents pertaining to the centennial celebration in 1987. The documents include ceremony recordings, concert programs, handouts, flyers, some correspondence, exhibit displays, and meeting minutes. Also includes information from the Jewish Ceremonial Art Exhibition at Duke University in 1988, in which the synagogue participated as part of the centennial. One folder includes photocopied advertisements from Jewish businesses in Durham from the 1880s. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
  Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  - Beth-El Preschool, 1968-2004; undated; 1
    - Carnival of the Arts, 1975-1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Flyers, form letters, publicity notes, meeting agendas, reports
    - Carnival of the Arts Financial Summaries, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      Financial summaries
    - Carnival of the Arts Publicity Materials, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
      Flyers, handouts, newspaper clippings
    - Exhibit Boards, 1998-2004 (Box 24)
      Contain photos of preschool activities on display boards
    - Financial Records, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      Notes, budgets
    - Financial Records Bound Volume, 1968-1969 (Box 28)
      Bound volume of billing information and employee payment records
    - Folded note, undated (Box 1)
    - Founding of Beth-El Preschool, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      Correspondence, flyer, article
    - Insurance Accident Forms, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Letters to Parents, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
      Form letters
    - Monthly Financial Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Pen Pal Letters, 1988; undated (Box 1)
    - Planning Notes, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
      Meeting notes, directories
    - Quarterly Tax Records, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
      Federal tax documents
    - Rosters, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - Supplies Expenditures, 1969-1974 (Box 1)
    - Teacher Applications and Letters, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - Teacher Contracts, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Teacher Files, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Board and Governance, 1939-2008; 2
    - Board and General Meeting Minutes Bound Volume, 1939-1951 (Box 27)
      Bound volume of handwritten meeting notes with various handouts taped in, including:correspondence, financial reports, budgets, and typed notes
    - Board and General Meeting Minutes, 1948-1984; 8 folders (Box 2)
      Agendas, meeting minutes
    - Board and General Meeting Minutes Bound Volume, 1975-1977 (Box 27)
      Bound volume of handwritten meeting notes with various handouts taped in, including: form letters, financial reports, budgets, requests, and typed notes
    - Board and General Meeting Minutes Bound Volume, 1978-1980 (Box 26)
    - Board Member Materials, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
      Agendas, congregation letters, financial reports, proposed budgets
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1979-1985; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1985-1991; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Board and General Meeting Minutes, 1992-2008; 13 folders (Box 4)
    - Board Meeting Schedules, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940-2005; undated; 3
    - Sagar, Steven, 1980-1985; 9 folders (Box 5)
      Official correspondence with Rabbi Sagar while serving at Beth-El Synagogue
    - Miscellaneous, 1940-1950 (Box 5)
      ands
    - Miscellaneous, 1951-2005; 3 folders (Box 6)
      Official correspondence between Beth-El Synagogue and various individuals and official organizations, including the American Association for Jewish Education, American Zionist Youth Commission, Hebrew Theological College, United Synagogue of America, and Yeshiva University
    - Zionist Letter, undated (Box 6)
      To William Bane, Secretary Durham Zionist District; written in Hebrew
    - General Correspondence, 1969-1990 (Box 29)
  - Subject Files, 1881-2009; undated; 4
    - Advertisements, 1881; undated (Box 6)
      Photocopies of various merchandise advertisements
    - Alpine Summit Meeting, 1986 (Box 6)
      Form letter, handout, newsletter
    - Archival List, undated (Box 6)
      Numbered list of archival materiels from Beth-El Synagogue
    - Beth-El Sisterhood Meeting Minutes Bound Volume, 1955-1959 (Box 26)
      Bound volume of handwritten meeting notes
    - Beth-El Sisterhood Meeting Minutes Bound Volume, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - Beth-El Sisterhood, 1959-1995 (Box 6)
      Form letters, scripts, news clippings, agendas, membership lists
    - Beth-El Synagogue Building, 1920 (Box 6)
      Photocopied photos of original synagogue in downtown Durham, North Carolina
    - Book of Life, 1920 (Box 23)
      Durham Hebrew Congregation, Beth-El Synagogue
    - Golden Book of Life, 1924-1963 (Box 23)
      Beth-El Synagogue, Durham, NC; In memory of Louis Gladstein
    - By-laws, 1907 (Box 6)
    - Calendar Cover, 2001-2002; 3.5 inch floppy disc containing 1 file; less than 1 MB. (Box 25, Digital-materials RL11336-SET-0001)
      Includes one MS Publisher file of the "First Annual Beth El Kitchen Calendar" in PUB format.
    - Cemetary Deeds, 1916-1933 (Box 6)
    - Cemetary Deed and Freedman Center Deed, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Centennial Celebration of Beth-El, 1988; undated (Box 6)
      Notes, meeting minutes, concert programs
    - Centennial Time Capsule, 1987 (Box 6)
      Questionnaires
    - Centennial Events, 1987; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Programs, pamphlets, correspondence, handouts, flyers, news clippings, photographs
    - Centennial Exhibit Boards, 1987-1998 (Box 24)
      Includes congregation signatures, photo of synagogue interior
    - Centennial Items for Bulletin Board Display, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Centennial Recordings, 1988 (Box 25)
      17 April 1988; three VHS tapes of closing ceremonies, Schpiel Play, and "Torah as Lived by Music and Martin Lakin"
    - Check Stubs, 1977-1995; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Chevra Kadisha Correspondence, 1971-1990 (Box 7)
      Letters, agreements, receipts
    - Chevra Kadisha for Eisenberg, Gertrude, 1983 (Box 7)
      Letters, agreements, clippings
    - Chevra Kadisha Documents, 1988-1995 (Box 7)
      Funeral checklists, summaries, notes
    - Chevra Kadisha Funeral Guides, undated (Box 8)
      Handbooks, newspaper clipping
    - Chevra Kadisha Funeral Preparations and Notes, 1997; undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
      Meal of condolence, burial, Chevra
    - Chevra Kadisha Funeral Summaries, 1985-1997 (Box 8)
      Obituaries, forms, tahara ritual, certificates
    - Chevra Kadisha Text: Jewish Ritual, Reality, and the Response at the End of Life, 2007 (Box 8)
    - Chevra Kadisha Memorial Prayers and Books of Remembrance, 1989; undated (Box 8)
    - Chevra Kadisha Miscellaneous, 1972-2006; undated (Box 8)
      Burial plots, funeral checklists, handbooks, plot deeds, condolence emails
    - Chevra Kadisha Volunteers, 1982-1989; undated (Box 8)
      Volunteer forms
    - Confirmation, 1983-1987 (Box 8)
      Handouts, form letters, readings
    - Confirmation and Baptism Documents, undated (Box 9)
      Certificates, newsletters
    - Congregation Membership Lists, 1965; 1974; 2000 (Box 9)
    - Congregation Constitutions, 1907-2007; undated; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Construction of New Synagogue, 1920; undated (Box 9)
      Meeting minutes, correspondence
    - Construction of New Synagogue and Cornerstone Ceremony, 1921; 1957-1965; undated (Box 9)
      Reports, photograph, booklet
    - Construction Proposal, 1958 (Box 9)
    - Construction blueprints/plans for synagogue, 1956 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Durham Hebrew Cemetary plots blueprint/maps, 1938 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Famous Congregation Members, 1955; undated (Box 9)
      Newspaper clippings, photographs, correspondence
    - Financial Papers, 1886-1984 (Box 9)
      Miscellaneous reports and ledgers
    - Financial Records Bound Volume, 1942 (Box 22)
      Ledger of synagogue financial transactions
    - Financial Records Bound Volume, 1954-1957 (Box 28)
      Ledger of financial transactions
    - Financial Records Binder, 1969-1984 (Box 22)
      Binder of payments for maintenance of cemetary graves
    - Financial Records Floppy Discs, 1995-1999 and undated; Two 3.5 inch floppy discs containing 10 files; 1.29 MB. (Box 25, Digital-materials RL11336-SET-0001)
      Spreadsheets with synagogue financial data in MS xls format.
    - Financial Records Bound Volume, 1972-1978 (Box 22)
    - Financial Reports, 1948-1973 (Box 9)
    - Foundation Contacts, 1985 (Box 9)
      Blumenthal, National Foundation for Jewish Culture
    - Forming a Minyan: The History of Durham Beth-El Congregation, undated (Box 9)
      Includes guide on how to conduct an interview
    - Freedman Center Dedication, 1989 (Box 9)
      Photographs, program, report
    - Historical Notes, 1950-1987 (Box 9)
      Beth-El Synagogue newspaper clippings and building fund correspondence
    - History of Beth-El Synagogue, 1987 (Box 9)
      By Rogoff, Leonard; includes correspondence with author
    - History of Beth-El Synagogue Binder, 1909-2003 (Box 10)
      Photocopies of newspaper clippings and photographs, reports
    - History of Building Beth-El Synagogue Center, 1957 (Box 10)
      Typed report
    - Histories, 1951-1953; undated (Box 10)
      Handwritten and typed accounts of members' history at synagogue
    - Jewish Ceremonial Art Exhibition, 1985-1988; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Duke University; newspaper clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, articles, curatorial guide, agendas, draft descriptions
    - Jewish Education Week, 1984 (Box 10)
      Photographs, pamphlet, letter
    - Jewish Hsitorical Society 12th Annual Conference, 1987 (Box 10)
      Handouts, newspaper clipping photocopies
    - Jewish Relief Committee, 1916 (Box 24)
      Flyers of servicemen from Durham, NC
    - Jewish Relief Committees for World War I, 1916-1920; undated (Box 10)
      Flyers, handouts
    - Judging Justices, undated (Box 10)
      Statement by Terry Sanford
    - Ladies' Aid Society Meeting Minutes, 1930-1944; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, 1924-1987 (Box 10)
      Handouts, flyers, reports
    - Miscellaneous Committee Reports, 2001-2006 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Exhibits, 1961-1985 (Box 10)
      Photographs, captions, newspaper clipping photocopies
    - Miscellaneous Legal Papers, 1899-1963 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous Handouts, 1975; undated (Box 11)
    - Music and Films, 1983; undated (Box 11)
      Catalogues, flyers
    - National Foundation of Jewish Culture, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
      Applications and lists of traveling art shows, correspondence
    - North Carolina Humanities Committee, 1986 (Box 11)
      Proposal guidelines
    - Orthodox Kahilia, undated (Box 11)
      Information sheets
    - Puzzle, 1984 (Box 11)
      Puzzle letter sent by Rabbi Steven Sagar to the Bar Mitzvah Class of 1984
    - Rabbis, 1938-1987 (Box 11)
      Photographs of and corrspondence from Beth-El Synagogue rabbis
    - Rabbi's Banquets, 1988-1991 (Box 11)
      Receipts, correspndence, expense logs
    - Religion and Public Education, 1988 (Box 11)
      Class taught by Rabbi Steven Sagar at University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; syllabus
    - Retirement Plan, undated (Box 11)
      Documents for Rabbi Steven Sagar's retirement plan
    - Reconstructionist Rabbinical Association Placement, 1985 (Box 11)
      Placement documents
    - Sheet Music, undated (Box 11)
      Photocopies of "Nobody Knows You When You're Down and Out" by Jimmy Cox; "Downtown" by Tony Hatch; "Who Will Buy" by Lionel Bart; "Get Me to the Church on Time" by Frederick Loewe
    - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1997 (Box 11)
      Beth-El Staff
    - Teachers' Tea Event, 1959 (Box 11)
      Form letter, script
    - Teachers' Tea Program, undated (Box 11)
    - Tree of Achievements Bronze Cast, 1992 (Box 11)
      Planning documents and photographs
    - Tzadatsah (Charity Work), 1985-2009 (Box 12)
      Certificate, handouts, correspondence, reports
    - Zionism, 1938-1987 (Box 12)
      Flyers, reports
    - The Jewish Theological Seminary of America, and College Laison, 1960 (Box 29)
    - Teachers' Tea and Chanukah Carnival, 1960; 1971 (Box 29)
    - Installation Affair, 1965 (Box 29)
    - Torah Fund Residence Hall, approximately 1990 (Box 29)
    - National Sabbath Observance Effort, 1952 (Box 29)
    - National Women's League of the United States of America, 1960-1965 (Box 29)
    - Women's League for Conservative Judaism, 1985-1989; 4 folders (Box 29)
    - High Holiday Babysitting Co-op, 1990-1991 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous Materials, approximately 1957-1980s (Box 29)
    - Meeting Notebook, 1951-1955 (Box 29)
    - Unidentified Scroll (Box 30)
      This folder contains an unidentified scroll.
    - Exposed Negative Cassettes, Zarkin, 2001 (Box 30)
      This folder contains two exposed negative cassettes
    - Stamp: Property of Beth El Sisterhood (Box 30)
      This folder contains a stamp with the legend "Property of Beth El Sisterhood."
    - Chumash Plates Disc, approximately 1990s-2000s; One compact disc 700 MB, 80-minute. (Box 25, Optical-disc RL11336-OP-0006)
      Electronic records may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services with questions.
    - Newspapers and Schedule, approximately 1960-1990 (Oversize-folder 2)
- Jewish History, 1908-1987; undated; 2
  The Jewish History series contains historical accounts of Jewish life in Durham and Chapel Hill, and includes personal biographies of several congregant members. Includes a full manuscript of "History of Jewish Community of Durham and Chapel Hill, 1887-1987" as well as Notes from "From Pine Street to Watts Street: An Oral History of the Jews of Durham, NC." Also includes naturalization papers and petitions from several individuals in the 1910s. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Concentration Camps, undated (Box 12)
    Shopiro, Karin; Dachau handout
  - Durham-Chapel Hill Jewish Community History Project, 1986 (Box 12)
    Notes, outlines, reports
  - History of Jewish Community of Durham and Chapel Hill, 1887-1987 (Box 12)
    Hanft, Sheldon, Ph.D. and Leonard Rogoff
  - Durham County Naturalization Petitions, 1908-1922 (Box 12)
    Swartz, Sam; Hockfeld, Hyman
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12)
    Certificate in Hebrew
  - Miscellaneous Biographies, undated (Box 12)
  - Naturalization Papers, 1917 (Box 12)
  - Notes from "From Pine Street to Watts Street: An Oral History of the Jews of Durham, NC", 1986 (Box 12)
    Gruber, Robin
  - Passport, 1959 (Box 12)
    Berman, Samuel
  - Personal Stories of the Establishment of Israel, 1993 (Box 12)
    Durham, NC residents
  - Sam Margolis: In Memoriam, 2004; 3.5 floppy disc containing 1 file. Less than 1 MB. (Box 25, Digital-materials RL11336-SET-0001)
    Document file in MS Word format.
  - Southern Jewish History, 1987 (Box 12)
    Contents of binder; handouts, correspondence
- Photographs, 1900-2004; undated; 3
  Photographs primarily consists of documentation of congregant members at a variety of synagogue and Beth El Preschool events. Includes a 1900 photograph of the Gladsteins storefront with congregant members, the early Durham Hebrew Congregation, and the original cathedral-style synagogue in downtown Durham. Also includes photos from the Jewish Ceremonial Art exhibition, the photo album, "A Photographic History of Beth El," and formal portraits of congregant presidents and rabbis. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Beth-El photographs from Maxine Stern, 2010-2011; 1 CD containing 75 files; 57.3 MB. (Box 25, Digital-materials RL11336-SET-0001)